so i had a few
uh questions sent to me
and they all seem to
be about rupa
what is rupa
yeah give me information about rupa
give me information about rupa
so that i can understand it
so that can be
liberated from my suffering and
and
i think you can always answer someone
you know you can give them the
definition the dictionary definition
[Music] such as that
such as that
you can give them an english word
matter form
resistance
and that will all be on the level of you
know abstract information yeah
and will make no difference in that
sense it doesn't perfect
it doesn't apply to the place where it
should apply
it's already like how do you
how should you regard the phenomenon of
ruba that is in your experience
that is in your experience
so what is it upon your experience
practically speaking what is the first
trooper pretty much the framework of all other
pretty much the framework of all other
as well your body yeah so it's
inconceivable you when you think
abstractly you think on account of the
present body present functioning body
but it is paid with life and so on
so there is no other group or other
understanding group on any other level
will be misunderstanding it
so
understand group on the level of the
body you understood all your you escaped
rupa won't find the footing in this
experience anymore and so on
so the body and
but you you cannot experience
the body
without just perceiving it
i can't just experience
body without without
perceiving it
yeah sure the experience of the body is
perception yeah
yeah
but i can't just body you can't just
have pure rupa
without any without the aggregate of
perception without well without other
aggregates it's always the five
aggregates practically speaking then
practically speaking then
understanding
of uh
the the group
the group
the only rupa that you
have the only rupa through which you can
experience the
the
your body the loop of your body
uh
practically speaking how would
how would you understand that what is
there to be understood
like is it physical examination of your
form for which you're basically just
for which you're basically just
observing it with your senses
that would not be on the level of
understanding they'll be on the level of
you know collecting random information
about the properties of that form
externally through observation
now we're talking about
is understanding your body
internally so understanding
the relationship
that you have internally with the like
fantasity the presence of your body for
what it is
so the mind that's paired with the body
needs understanding on the level of that
pairing not on the level of the external
not on the level of the external
appearance and observation and
sensations and so on all of that is
secondary to that
primordial form
primordial rupa
you don't understand the relationship
yeah so and that relationship doesn't
have uh
it doesn't have infinite amount of
possibilities or pathways it's always
going to go down either ownership or not
ownership taking it permanently as permanent when
taking it permanently as permanent when
it's not permanent taking it as mine
when it's not mine taking it as
pleasurable when it's not pleasurable
that's it
that's what needs to be understood on
that fundamental level on that internal
side of
you having the body you're being paired
within the body
you've been you've been paid you've been
fair with the body but even thought of
me and i am implies the image of their
body so it's all within so it you can't
that's where you can't separate the root
by examine it
individually from other aggregates or or
kind of access it without the regular
whatever else it's the five aggregates
it's the experience as a whole so it's
within those aggregates just remove the
ignorance in regard to certain
properties of the aggregates because it same
of the aggregates because it same
applies what i said non-ownership
non-delight nothing is pleasurable
seeing it as dangerous seeing it is not
worth delighting in
that applies to the body applies to the
feelings applies to the perception
applies to the intention applies to the
consciousness applies to the fibroids
applies to the fibroids
those universal recognitions
so if you just practice in regard to the
body those recognitions you are
practicing in regard to the phylogreats
if you practicing your other physics you
practice then you go to the body
but practically speaking even the
thought of five aggregates
you know it's more often than not it's
abstract to people
you know the five ugly it's okay one two
my perception but you know it's the body
it's the experience here and now before
i start thinking about the fire rates
that's already what finally leads up
self-awareness of this moment here and
now that endures it's already what the
five agreements are affected we do put
on assumptions and so on a lack of
clarity
why mindfulness of the body developed to
the extent necessary for the final
knowledge will approach all of the
ignorance and that's what mindfulness of the body
and that's what mindfulness of the body
is
sustaining composing rightly
that framework on the right level on
that internal recognition of the
framework of the body the form given
manifestation and so on
not on the level of or i shall observe
stuff with my body on the body within
the body for as long as it takes until i
get the magical recognition of some you
know divine truth of liberation
seeing the body on the right seeing the
body on the right level recognizing it
as a phenomenon that's why i said before
like seeing the body as peripherally
already and during there before you
start looking at it directly
that's the body that's the level that
all these understandings need to apply
before you start thinking about the body
the reason you can start thinking about
a body because it's already there
peripherally enduring
so you want to start seeing that without
needing to look at and make it forward
make it something you need to stare at
in order for it to exist
and by seeing that you ultimately start
seeing this
this kind of
disconnect between between you
between between you
and the body
there's this
there is a well yeah that separation is
kind of gratuitously generated
through mistaking what the actual body
is
because if you see the body and the
aggregates on the level of that
peripheral everything is within that so there is no
everything is within that so there is no
more disconnect so the widow's
describing he says it doesn't matter
like whatever form there is uh past
future present big small personal
impersonal delightful ugly
um
every any possible attribute describes
it he knows form is there means he's not
concerned with the specifics of it he
sees the framework on that peripheral
level of the form is present
whatever feeling past future present
personal impersonal
delighting suffering any type of feeling
he doesn't matter he knows feeling a
feeling is there
same goes for perception intention
consciousness so he knows that form is there yeah but
so he knows that form is there yeah but
it doesn't matter what type yeah what
kind doesn't matter how it feels doesn't
matter how it's perceived what matters
is knowing the framework that the form
is present
yes so it's not about going into the
details the specifics not about
observing it directly yeah
so that's that's what the body is that's
what rupa is
rupa is recognizing body on that
peripheral level
without directly attending to it
that's rupa yeah that's practical but
rupa is for you that's why after rupa is
used interchangeably with kaya like like
for word for body in bali
we always talk about the elements you
know it's made up of elements yeah
so well you can you can now extend that
peripheral context
so that body that you see peripherally
you can now start seeing either solidity
fluidity airy fiery space all of that on the
airy fiery space all of that on the
peripheral level not on the level of
your focusing meditation objects
on on which you can't even see this mere
body you can't observe directly you can only
you can't observe directly you can only
think you're observing it through
watching some random secondary
sensations of it
so so now
i have a clear
context of the body mindful of the body
in that way on peripheral level as a
necessary basis for
you and i sitting here together talking
discussing this mindfully but in the
present moment while the knowledge of
the body being there behind this with
like as a framework to this endures
and so as i do that
do that
i'm aware of that
i'm not
creating that situation but i'm mindful
of the body and then
and then
then what yeah
what do you think
what's next yeah what do you think
what's next
well if i start to think about it
i see that it's
i'm subjected to it
no i mean what's next what do you need
to do next
you described okay i'm mindful of the
body okay great so what what's next then
what do you do is that it
depending from mindfulness to the body
is that enough but what else do you need
to do well i need to well if i read in
the sutures i need to recognize certain
qualities of that body
so how would you go about doing that
by staying mindful of it so okay so but
not changing anything in the way yeah so
by protecting the mindfulness that you
already developed so basically means you need to
developed so basically means you need to
protect it for a longer time
until you see what needs to be seen
within it for which you already have
information yeah so it's a nietzsche
yeah so you can tell the audience is a nature
so you can tell the audience is a nature
but until you recognize them in nature
in that which you now have which you
protect on the right level
you won't be on each other that you're
seeing until you recognize it for where
it is it will be just abstractly concept
of religion which is fine you can't help
thinking it but that's the important
part to recognize like okay so now i
need to do something else
and then people forget that whatever
else you need to do which yes there is
factually things you need to do but none
of those things
should be done at the expense
of mindfulness of the body on that
peripheral level
so that must remain unchanged you must
protect that
so then doing
of these other things must be within
that not instead or after that or
something like that
that's your priority well that's the
framework that's what that's where the
solution is
so yes you need to like develop it
further within that not instead of it
not in place of it like okay now i'll
remove this because i did it let me do
the next thing because that's completed
no it's one within that within that
within that so in other words
all you need to do is practice
mindfulness to the extended muscles of
the body to the extent necessity for the
final knowledge so if you see the body
correctly on that peripheral level
you don't need to do anything on the
level of doing but that's the problem
well that's exactly so it's the pull the
pressure to do something
at the expense of which you end up not
doing what you know what you're already
doing rightly
so you kind of get you you you see you
have mindfulness of the body it's
basically playing the the string instrument if
playing the the string instrument if
it's too tight too loose there'll be a
horrible sound
but if you get the right amount of
tension then this sounds perfect
so being mindful of the body on the
level of that peripheral correctly
sustaining that is what that right
amount of tension is it's money
exactly yeah so the more you sustain it
the more of samadhi you will have
but then of course the natural tendency
is to kind of you know either slack it
or tighten it
the natural tendency is to fall from
that middle way
and if person doesn't recognize the
middle way for what it is as something
that they must protect and stay with
then they will almost out of a sense of
duty for practice
go on and start doing things that will
compromise that right amount of tension
and they'll become too tense
so they will fall from the practice or
they'll become too loose so they'll fall
from the practice
so that's why you can't have too much of
mindfulness you can have too much of pondering about
you can have too much of pondering about
properties of things and nature of
things and so on too much of not
pondering too much of just being you
know composed
but you can't have too much of
recognizing the right context the right
framework so in other words what do you do next
so in other words what do you do next
when you developed
recognition of the body of rhubarb form
on that peripheral level is something
that endures there
that doesn't belong to you but it's a
necessary basis for the entire world
you're experiencing here and now
well probably first thing you do is nothing
probably first thing you do is nothing
except protect it
don't don't sort of neglect it don't
ignore it
and don't try to
don't try to
speed speed it up so to speak
but actually allow it to endure and and
try to become more and more familiar
with it for less and less
effort and that's how you become
proficient in playing music basically as
well and you immediately recognize the the
and you immediately recognize the the
tune the right
the right amount of tension for the
perfect music
and how do you then protect that
furniture sensory strength guiding the sensors you
sensory strength guiding the sensors you
can't have too much of virtue that's
impossible so even if you're doubtful about
so even if you're doubtful about
everything else
no
how to address that what are the answers
to all these questions
five aggregates consciousness infinite
consciousness states
all of that is your own mind trying to
throw you from that right amount of
tension that's based on the right
recognition of mindfulness it's
effortless when the music starts to flow it's
when the music starts to flow it's
effortless so
so
no doubt the mind will be coming up with
his with his thoughts and think doubts
but you recognize okay so that's
something that i must include within
that peripheral recognition of the body
that's enduring there not other way
around not put that doubt first and then trying
not put that doubt first and then trying
to solve this peripheral condition of
the body and during that that i already
seen and have endured rightly
so whatever yeah so whatever so
whatever thought arises whatever feeling
around us whatever perception arises he
sees it
in relation uh it is dependently
arrested on one yes on this body on the
board so he he still he doesn't he
refuses to put that first and that
peripheral condition the body is second
right he keeps the peripheral
conditional body first and whatever else
rises second so whatever else arises he
feels he perceives he intends detached
from it
he feels because the right order
protects him from attachment
[Music] and that's it what do you do next
and that's it what do you do next
nothing just keep doing that
until all the passion is gone
how long that would be well i don't know
half a day one day seven days seven
weeks uh seven months seven years as
satya patana says because so you keep in
that context mindfulness of the body and
whatever is
arising in your experience
you see it in relation to that yeah and
then it's
then that that well that's the whole
point is undoing it's undoing the
passion in regard to things that's why
that's why you crave for all these
answers about the five aggregates and
patient fathers and stuff because it's
all pressuring you with that passion
that you want to be free from
but obviously that's that's the catch
finding the answers for it perpetuates
the passion because you act out of
passion so sooner or later you have to recognize
so sooner or later you have to recognize
that if you want to practice rightly
and then refrain
from putting those questions first
and everything else second to it until
you find the answer
because fundamentally you end up acting
out of pressure as we said so many times
but instead the pressuring questions the
pressure and doubts and so on what next
and whatever else your mind might be
throwing at you
you put that second to that peripherally
recognized mindfulness of the body
that's enduring there and endure it
endure the pressure is second and don't
let your mind don't allow yourself don't
choose it first and then start acting
out of which will put your recognition
of the body as peripheral thing and
during the second or even disappear you
will lose mindfulness in another way
and just
back to that and well the suit of
exactly referring to that when he feels
a feeling he feels it detached attached
yeah it feels just unconnected to it so
and so when he feels a feeling
uh the pathogen of the ordinary person
who doesn't have mindfulness he feels a
feeling he feels connected to it
he doesn't see that
that this feeling is dependently arisen
yeah or is is uh
or is is uh
or the extent of feeling that it is it
is bounded by this body yeah which is
exactly he does because he doesn't see
the body it can only go so far as far as
the body goes
that's as far as the feeling will go for
him feeling goes as you said infinite
because he doesn't see the extent of it
yeah that's why the
that's why the
the infinite joy in the prospect of
centrality and the infinite dread in the
prospect of pain
because puttu's in untrained mind does
not recognize the extent of it
does not see what the right tune is
it does not see it as a risen upon that
peripherally enduring body that's there
because he doesn't see the peripheral
enduring body so all he sees is just my
feeling whatever
whatever
whatever i feel emotion it has no
boundary in a way it's exactly it's
bonus the ownership is boundless it's
infinite some starter
so when he feels a feeling
he feels it detached when he has
mindfulness of the body for example
he knows that it this feeling
terminates at the body that's it yeah he
sees that oh the presence of the body
has the presence of the feeling
the presence of that peripheral body is
the framework for this feeling
and the feeling cannot can surpass that
framework it's impossible
and that framework is seen as something
that doesn't belong to me
thus anything dependent upon the
framework can equally not belong to me
so whatever he feels perceives intent
it will be so detached
it will not be his cannot be his
because he unplugged it
he unplugged the framework that was
giving power to these things as his
yes this is a so
the ordinary person who spoke about it
last night the
when he feels
pleasure
in hindsight it goes so fast
time flies by when you're having fun
never when you're in pain adrenaline
yeah it's very small very slow
but then for a person because he's he is
connected with that sure
infinite boundless feeling of pain boundless
boundless feeling of pain boundless
infinite pleasure seemingly
but then when he's detached from that
where he sees the extent of that feeling
that it's dependent on a body which is
not mine which is
subject to change as well
then that
sense of
pain is forever or
if there is pleasure it's it's going to
be felt differently in terms of that
time it's not going to feel like it goes it goes
fast
yeah it will even out
or pain won't it won't feel like it's
dragging yeah because you're not resisting it
yeah because you're not resisting it
so
you know the thing don't last things
don't last long enough
when you want more of them right from
the start
when you crave for more of them then
things are just too cool
yeah things last too long when you don't want
things last too long when you don't want
them they're dragging when you don't
want even a second of it then every
second feels like an hour but now if you
remove that attitude
of delighting and pleasure and resisting
the pain then things just last for as
long as they last
which is neither long they're short it's
just for what they are
so that subjective side of time
in regard to things that are being felt
yeah for somebody who is detached from
feelings that evens out so it doesn't
matter if it's pain or pleasure
it does not imply oh look you know
when will this end because that's it
asking the question where will this pain
end i can't wait for it to end means oh
you really want to get rid of it but if
you don't have that attitude it doesn't
matter where it ends
because you're not resisting it in the
beginning not in the middle not in the
eminence so it doesn't matter how long
it lasts
which means you won't last longer
than you would otherwise
you see the extent of it yeah
you see that it's not infinite it's not
it yeah exactly because you don't fall
from recognizing the framework of that
peripherally enduring body
you also see that is that it cannot be
infinite exactly pleasure well you could
see that its infinity is within the
peripheral enduring body
which is not yours and it's going to
cease at some point so the infinity will
cease at some point
you can see this here the body here
dying or falling apart getting older
yeah see that all those are like
reflections that can help but the point
is to start seeing the body peripherally
that's what the right mindfulness is not
to look at it only yes i am aging
you know falling apart a male all these
sensations all of that is specific
you want to see the nature of it already
enduring there because of which i can
choose to look at specific things in
details and that nature has already been known
and that nature has already been known
like if i ask you do you have the
bodybuilding of course
so tap into that knowledge that's
already there learn how to see it with
the corner of your eye without needing
to make it a subject an object of your
direct attention that's the whole point
and you will be
you will be
able to do that more accurately
more likely let's say that
only if your physical behavior has been
if your physical behavior has been
restrained
purified and maintained in virtue
the whole domain of that peripheral
recognition with the corner of your eye
does not exist for somebody who is still
acting out of sensuality does not even
keep the precepts is not moderate does
not watch their speech and so on it just
doesn't exist so it doesn't matter how
much you try you're not going to see it
because it's covered up with a pollution
from your behavior
but if the behavior is unpolluted now
and somebody keeps telling you to desert
it with a corner of your eye
peripherally without looking at it
directly you will be able to
sooner or later you're going to start
seeing what that means there's a space
for you
yeah in a way yeah
well you are uncluttering it and then
you recognize it you